Finding Aid for School of Information (University of Michigan) Records 1901-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Information (University of Michigan) records 1904-2012 1926-1994
University of Michigan. School of Information.
Established as Department of Library Science; name later changed to School of Library Science, then School of Information and Library Studies. Materials relating to the teaching of library science at the university, including summer session and departmental files; administrative files of T. W. Koch, William W. Bishop, Rudolph H. Gjelsness, Wallace Bonk, Russell Bidlack, and Robert M. Warner; course materials and topical files; accreditation records, faculty minutes and photographs.
87301 Bimu C26 2
45 linear feet
3.29 GB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the School of Information (Donor 4855 ) in five major accessions, 1971, 1984, 1994, 1996, 2000 and 2010.
The records are open for research with the exception of some personnel, search and student related files. The restricted files a located in boxes 32-33.
The first formal program in library education at the University of Michigan began in 1909, when the University Librarian, Theodore Koch, began a summer program in "library methods." In 1918, Koch's successor, William Warner Bishop raised the entrance requirement for this summer program to a minimum of thirty hours of college credit.
In the spring of 1926, the Regents of the university authorized the creation of the Department of Library Science with Bishop as its chairman. Two degrees were offered: (1) a Bachelor of Arts, conferred after one year of work; and (2) a Master of Arts, conferred after two years of work. In 1930 a bachelor's degree was required for admission to the program.
Bishop retired from the department chairmanship in 1940 and was succeeded by Rudolph Gjelsness. In 1948, Gjelsness led a major curriculum revision which eliminated the bachelor's degree. Hereafter, the master's degree would be awarded after two semesters and one summer of work beyond the bachelor's degree. A doctoral program was also begun.
In 1964, Gjelsness reached the mandatory retirement age and was succeeded by Wallace J. Bonk. Bonk suffered a heart attack in 1967 and resigned the chairmanship to return to teaching. Professor Russell E. Bidlack, who had been a member of the faculty since 1950, was named acting chairman.
In November 1967, a panel of library leaders, which had been invited to visit and examine the department, recommended that the department be made a separate school. On October 18, 1968, the Regents approved the request and the change became effective on July 1, 1969.
Bidlack was named the school's first dean, a position which he held until his retirement in 1984. University Librarian Richard M. Dougherty became interim dean pending the arrival of Robert M. Warner as dean in April 1985. Warner came to the school after serving as Archivist of the United States. Under Warner, the school began to grow and change. The first visible sign of this came with the Regent's approval of the school's name change. As of July 1986, the School of Library Science officially became known as the School of Information and Library Studies. The name change reflected a changing emphasis in the curriculum and the changing nature of the field of librarianship through the use of computers and electronic media.
Warner left the deanship in 1992 to resume teaching at the school. A new dean search brought Daniel E. Atkins, an engineer and computer scientist, to the school. In 1996 the school's name was again changed, this time to the School of Information. This change reflected an even greater shift away from traditional library studies and towards the use of new information technologies. In September 1998 Atkins resigned as Dean. Gary Olson served as Acting Dean until December 1999, when John L. King assumed the deanship.
Administrators of Library Education/Deans
University Librarian
1877-1905 Raymond Cazallis Davis
1905-1915 Theodore Wesley Koch
1915-1941 William Warner Bishop
Chairman
1926-1940 William Warner Bishop
1940-1964 Rudolph Hjalmar Gjelsness
1964-1967 Wallace John Bonk
1967-1969 Russell Eugene Bidlack (Acting)
Dean
1969-1984 Russell Eugene Bidlack
1984-1985 Richard Martin Dougherty (Interim)
1985-1992 Robert Mark Warner
1992-1998 Daniel Ewell Atkins, III
1998-1999 Gary M. Olson (Acting)
2000- John L. King
School Histories -- Box 1
Office Files
1904-1964 -- Box 1-10
1930-1994 -- Box 22-30
1969-2001 -- Box 38-40
1954-1996 -- Box
Dean's Files
Russell E. Bidlack -- Box 19-21, 36
Richard M. Dougherty -- Box 36
Robert Warner -- Box 21, 22, 36
Course Materials -- Box 3, 4, 12, 26, 39-42
Faculty Meetings -- Box 5, 27, 37, 38
Photographs -- Box 34, 35
Audiotapes -- Box 31
The records of the School of Information (formerly the School of Library Science and most recently the School of Information and Library Studies) include 42.5 linear feet of material and cover ninety seven years from 1904 to 2001. The records document the development library education at Michigan from its beginnings as summer course to a full-fledged professional program that has, in recent years moved beyond traditional library science to incorporate a multi-disciplinary approach to information studies with a strong emphasis on the role of technology in the creation, dissemination and preservation of information.
The records, including correspondence, reports, committee minutes, administrative files and course descriptions, came to the library in five accessions. There is some overlap and continuation of series among the accessions.
The records are organized into seven series: Histories, Office Files, Dean's Files, Audiotapes, Photographs, Faculty Meetings, and Course Material.
Subjects:
Librarians--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Library Science.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; University of Michigan. School of Library Science.; University of Michigan. Summer Session.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Bonk, Wallace John, 1923-; Gjelsness, Rudolph H. (Rudolph Hjalmar), 1894-1968.; Koch, Theodore Wesley, 1871-1941.; Bidlack, Russell E. (Russell Eugene), 1920-; Warner, Robert M. (Robert Mark), 1927-2007.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Bidlack, Russell E. (Russell Eugene), 1920-; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Photographs.; University of Michigan--Classes.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; University of Michigan--Students.; Warner, Robert M. (Robert Mark), 1927-2007.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- School Histories
  - Histories (Box 1)
- Office files 1904-2001
  The Office Files series constitute the central file of the School of Information. It includes internal administrative correspondence, correspondence with the university's central administration and other academic departments and with professional organizations, other library schools, foundations and accrediting agencies. The organization of the files into chronological subseries reflects the way in which the files were transferred to the archives, or in some instances, changes in school administration. There is some overlap in time span of the subseries and some continuity of files between subseries. Each of the subseries is arranged in a single alphabetical sequence
  - 1904-1964
    The Office Files, 1904-1964 subseries (9.5 linear feet) is composed of the records of library education at the University of Michigan beginning in 1904. There are two reasons for the choice of 1964 as a dividing date. In 1964, Rudolph Gjelsness left the department after 24 years as its chairman. Secondly, the 1960s were a time of tremendous growth and change in the program, with its eventual elevation to a separate school in 1969.
    The 1904-1964 series is arranged alphabetically. It is largely composed of administrative correspondence. The primary correspondents are other libraries and library schools, library organizations, foundations, and other units within the university. Intra-university correspondence is located under the heading, "Michigan University." All correspondence with other library schools is located in "Library Schools." In particular, correspondence with the University of Illinois (1911-1964) and Columbia University (1926-1964) is rich. Other correspondence is scattered according to the name of the institution (i.e., American Library Association, Carnegie Endowment, and Moscow All-Union Lenin Library).
    Several files related to curriculum are also rich. "Curriculum Revisions and Discussions" includes documentation of the major curriculum revision of 1948. Course material is extensive and is found in three files: "Summer Sessions," "Course Material," and "Workshops." There are several folders, including correspondence, on the first formal summer session in 1909. Also of special interest are the fourteen folders of material from Bishop's seminar, L.S. 209.
    In addition, there is correspondence of individual faculty or administrators. The correspondence of Margaret Mann and Mary Parsons, both faculty members, is extensive. William Warner Bishop and Rudolph Gjelsness also have separate listings. However, their correspondence as department chairmen is scattered throughout the series.
    Other important files are Budgets (1941-1964), Faculty Meeting Minutes (1927-1964), and Annual Reports Material (1905-1916; 1932).
    - Admission Requirements 1939 (Box 1)
    - Alumni Data, classes of 1953, 1955 (Box 1)
      (summary of responses to questionnaires on position and salary)
    - Alumni Questionnaires, classes of 1929, 1930, 1951 (Box 1)
      (written comments)
    - American Library Annual, (article by Bishop on the creation of the department) 1927 (Box 1)
    - American Library Association
      - General Correspondence 1927-1964, 9 folders (Box 1)
      - Board of Education for Education (correspondence regarding accreditation) 1926-1953, 8 folders (Box 1)
      - Board of International Relations (Gjelsness correspondence) 1943-1948, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - Budget Committee 1946 (Box 1)
      - Catalog Code Revision 1944-1950, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Catalog Committee 1917-1926, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Committee on Committee Appointments 1934-1936 (Box 2)
      - Committee on Cooperation with Latin America 1940-1945 (Box 2)
      - Curriculum Study 1926-1931 (Box 2)
      - Editorial Board 1942-1949 (Box 2)
      - Executive Board 1944-1949 (Box 2)
      - Joint Committee on Foreign Students 1947-1948 (Box 2)
      - Joint Committee, International Relations Board and Board of Education 1947-1949 (Box 2)
      - Junior Members Round Table (Box 2)
      - Library Training Section 1928-1929 (Box 2)
      - Nominating Committee 1960-1961 (Box 2)
      - Personnel 1943-1950 (Box 2)
      - Professional Training Section 1931-1936 (Box 2)
      - Research Committee 1932-1933 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Public Library (letter regarding study of library needs in Ann Arbor) 1936 (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports material
      - 1905-1916 (Box 2)
      - 1932 (Box 2)
    - Association of American Library Schools 1920, 1929-1942, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Australia Institute of Librarians 1938-1941 (Box 2)
    - Beta Phi Mu 1950s (Box 2)
    - Bishop, William Warner
      (see also photographs)
      - Bishop Lectureships 1941-1942, 1947-1948, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Correspondence pertaining to the founding of the department 1926 (Box 2)
      - General (Box 2)
        (includes correspondence, memorial booklet printed in 1969 and 1917 gradebook)
      - Testimonial (pertaining to committee set up to honor Bishop upon his retirement) 1941 (Box 2)
    - Booksellers 1932-1937 (Box 2)
    - Boswell, Jessie 1910 (Box 2)
    - Bowker (R.R.) Co. 1934-1935 (Box 2)
    - Broomhall, Lydia 1909-1910 (Box 2)
    - Budget Fall 1941-Summer 1955, 27 folders (Box 2)
    - Budget Fall 1955-Winter 1964, 18 folders (Box 3)
    - Carnegie, Andrew (James Bertram, Secretary) 1907-1908 (Box 3)
    - Carnegie Corporation Studies in Library Science 1935-1937 (Box 3)
    - Carnegie Endowment Fellowships 1929-1940, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Carnegie Library School 1919-1938 (Box 3)
    - Certification of Librarians 1936-1937 (Box 3)
    - Class files
      - Class of 1892 (Box 3)
      - Class of 1928 (Box 3)
      - Class of 1931 (Box 3)
      - Class of 1933 (Box 3)
    - Cleveland Public Library 1912 (Box 3)
    - Cole, G.D.H. (article on academic freedom) 1936 (Box 3)
    - College of L.S.A. (course statistics) 1954-1963 (Box 3)
    - Colvin, Laura 1937-1943 (Box 3)
    - Counseling manual 1963 (Box 3)
    - Curriculum Revisions and Discussion
      - 1929-1931 (Box 4)
      - 1948 (Box 4)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 4)
    - Dana, John Cotton 1927-1928 (Box 4)
    - Decimal Classifications 1939-1940 (Box 4)
    - Deily, Robert H. 1949 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Metropolitan Library Club 1941-1942 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Public Library 1928-1960, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Doctoral Exams 1956
      - Bibliography and Book Selection (Box 4)
      - Bibliography of American History and Literature (Box 4)
      - Bibliography of English History and Literature (Box 4)
      - Public Libraries (Box 4)
    - Douglass, Robert H. 1947 (Box 4)
    - Drake items (miscellaneous mementos and programs from the Library Science Librarian) (Box 4)
    - Education for Librarianship 1937-1938 (Box 5)
    - Enoch Pratt Free Library (Baltimore) 1932-1933 (Box 5)
    - Ephemera 1933, 1936, 1938, Undated (Box 5)
    - Exchange of Librarians 1933-1937 (Box 5)
    - Extension Courses 1939-1945 (Box 5)
    - Faculty 1926-1940, 3 folders (Box 5)
      (correspondence and university memos regarding relations with individual faculty)
    - Ford Foundation 1949 (Box 5)
    - Gjelsness, Rudolph H.
      - American Library Association, correspondence 1944-1952 (Box 5)
      - General, correspondence 1952-1957 (Box 5)
      - Orr Complaint 1963 (Box 5)
    - Institute for Trustees 1941-1942 (Box 5)
    - Internship in Library Training 1935-1936 (Box 5)
    - Kellogg Foundation Workshops (Box 5)
    - Kingsley, James 1946-1948 (Box 5)
    - Lectures (by guest speakers or visiting professors) 1926-1946, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Library Associations 1930-1949, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Library Methods (writings of Bishop on instruction in library methods) 1922-1926 (Box 5)
    - Library of Congress 1926-1932 (Box 5)
    - Library Practice 1931-1933 (Box 5)
    - Library Press 1929-1939 (Box 5)
    - Library Schools
      - Alliance College 1935-1936 (Box 5)
      - American Correspondence School of Librarianship 1925-1926 (Box 5)
      - Atlanta. Carnegie Library School 1922-1927 (Box 5)
      - Atlanta Library School 1940-1941 (Box 5)
      - Boone Library School 1926-1935 (Box 5)
      - California-Berkeley. University 1927-1959 (Box 5)
      - California-Los Angeles. University 1956-1959 (Box 5)
      - Chicago. University 1927-1959, 4 folders (Box 5)
      - Columbia University 1926-1964, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Denmark, American Graduate School 1949 (Box 6)
      - Denver University 1936-1937 (Box 6)
      - Drexel Institute 1907-1944 (Box 6)
      - Emory University 1930-1941 (Box 6)
      - Hampton Institute 1933-1939 (Box 6)
      - Illinois. University 1911-1964, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - London University 1928-1941 (Box 6)
      - Michigan State University 1953-1961 (Box 6)
    - Library Science Abstracts 1933-1934 (Box 6)
    - Library Science Round Table 1927-1928 (Box 6)
    - Library Science Study Hall 1951-1954 (Box 6)
      (includes annual reports for the Study Hall, renamed the Library Science Library in 1955)
    - Loan Fund 1931-1939 (Box 6)
    - Maginn, Gertrude 1927-1928 (Box 6)
    - Mann, Margaret
      - Correspondence 1921-1938, 6 folders (Box 6)
      - General, 2 folders (Box 6)
        (includes biographical sketches, tributes, and correspondence about Mann)
      - Margaret Mann Scholarships 1938-1940 (Box 6)
    - Marinelli, Anne V. (research project) 1958-1959 (Box 6)
    - Michigan. University
      - Advisers of Women 1928-1929 (Box 7)
      - Bureau of Appointments 1928-1931 (Box 7)
      - Bureau of Cooperation with Educational Institutions 1935-1936 (Box 7)
      - Bureau of Government 1932-1933 (Box 7)
      - College of Literature, Science, and Arts 1926-1946, 6 folders (Box 7)
      - Dean of Students 1940-1945 (Box 7)
      - Department of Fine Arts 1934-1937 (Box 7)
      - Department of Library Science (administrative correspondence of the department) 1926-1963, 28 folders (Box 7)
      - Graduate Council 1936-1940 (Box 7)
      - Graduate School 1921-1948, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - School of Education 1929-1950 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Librarian 1937-1943 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Libraries (Goodrich's correspondence) 1912-1914 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Library Association
      - General 1931-1951, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - McHale's Scrapbook (Box 8)
    - Michigan Library Survey 1938-1939 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Daily 1956 (Box 8)
    - Mitchell, Sydney 1926-1927 (Box 8)
    - Moscow All Union Lenin Library 1929-1934 (Box 8)
    - Odon, Yvonne 1946-1953 (Box 8)
    - Parsons, Mary 1933-1961, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Pendleton Memorial Library 1925-1927 (Box 8)
    - Placement 1928-1960, 9 folders (Box 8)
    - Predeek, Albert 1938-1939 (Box 8)
    - Pritchard, Martha 1924-1925 (Box 8)
    - Prytz, Mrs. Elizabeth 1941 (Box 8)
    - Publishers 1927-1932 (Box 8)
    - Reference 1927-1940, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Remodeling-Third Floor Plans 1962 (Box 8)
    - Rockefeller Foundation 1943 (Box 8)
    - Ross, Cecil 1919-1920 (Box 8)
    - Rothrock, Mary Utopia 1949 (Box 8)
    - Scholarships 1926-1929 (Box 8)
    - School Librarians Training 1936-1960, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - School Status (correspondence regarding 1954 request) 1954 (Box 8)
    - Stearns, Leslie 1926-1927 (Box 8)
    - Student Directories 1950-1952 (Box 8)
    - Student Statistics
      - 1925-1943 (Box 8)
      - 1954-1956 (Box 8)
    - Students-Masters Candidates 1953-1954 (Box 8)
    - Summer Sessions 1904-1953, 37 folders (Box 9)
      (includes correspondence and course materials, five folders on the 1909 session)
    - Swinton, R.S. 1953 (Box 9)
    - U.S. Office of Education-Conference on Research in Librarianship 1939 (Box 9)
    - Van Deusen, Neil C. 1949-1951 (Box 9)
      (see also photograph)
    - War Department 1921-1922 (Box 9)
    - Wead, Eunice 1931-1936 (Box 9)
    - Williamson, C.C. 1922-1923 (Box 9)
    - Wilson, Edith R. 1927-1928 (Box 9)
    - Workshops
      - 1953 Workshop (Box 9)
      - 1953 Workshop on School Library Problems (Box 9)
      - 1954 Workshop (Box 9)
      - 1954 Workshop on School Library Problems (Box 9)
      - 1955 School Library Workshop (Box 9)
      - 1955 Workshop on School Library Problems (Box 9)
      - 1955 Librarian as a Community Leader (Box 9)
      - 1956 Workshop (Box 9)
      - 1956 Workshop on Library Science (L.S. 149) (Box 10)
      - 1956 Workshop on Public Library Planning for Adult Education Services (L.S. 273) (Box 10)
      - 1957 Workshops (Box 10)
      - 1957 Workshop on School Library Problems (Box 10)
      - 1958 Workshop (Box 10)
      - 1958 Workshop on Library Service for Teen-agers (Box 10)
      - 1959 Workshop (Box 10)
      - 1960 Workshop (Box 10)
      - 1961 Workshop (Box 10)
  - 1964-1984
    The Office Files, 1964-1984 subseries (9 linear feet) is composed of the records of the school from 1964 through 1984, though there is very little material from Wallace Bonk's time as chairman (1964-1967). The subseries encompasses the school's administration and operation and has several interesting files.
    Accreditation relates to the school's reaccreditation in 1974 by the American Library Association Committee on Accreditation (COA). Prior to the COA site visit, the school undertook a self-study and submitted its report to the COA. Most of the materials relate to this self-study process. Overseen by a steering committee, chaired by Rosemary Magrill, the self-study was made up of six subcommittees: Faculty; Governance, Administration, and Financial Support; Physical Resources and Facilities; Program Goals and Objectives; Questionnaires; and Students. Each committee was made up of faculty, student, and alumni representatives. Correspondence and the final COA report are also included. The material provides detailed insight into all aspects of the school's operation.
    Affirmative Action contains correspondence and reports regarding the School of Library Science's efforts to meet the university's 1969 commitment to ten percent minority enrollment. There are also materials on the Black Action Movement and on an allegedly racist film ("The Speaker") purchased by the school. Alumnus-in-Residence refers to an annual program, begun in 1969, which brought distinguished alumni to the university for discussion with students about current issues in librarianship. Included in this file are programs, correspondence, and memos.
    The Committee on Institutional Cooperation (C.I.C.) contains correspondence regarding the development and operation of a joint doctoral program in library science. Course Material is limited for this series, with material for only three classes. Only L.S. 813, Bidlack's Trends and Issues seminar, is extensively represented. The Knapp Project contains materials about the school's experimental program in school library management from 1971 to 1974. Types of materials include grant proposals, budgets, correspondence, committee meeting notes, research data, and the interim and final reports.
    An especially useful file is School Status. It includes materials relating to the Regents' 1968 decision to make the Department of Library Science into a separate school. Included is Bonk's 1964 statement to Dean Haber requesting school status, and correspondence from 1963 to 1972. The largest part of the file relates to the 1967 visit by a panel of library leaders. There are numerous documents on various aspects of the department's operation.
    In the subseries, there are several file headings which require little description. Among these are Budgets, Faculty Minutes, and Workshops, for which there are also records in the 1904-1964 subseries. Both the Curriculum Committee and the Long-Range Planning Committee files are composed of minutes, memos, notes, and correspondence of the committees. In later accessions, Faculty Minutes are treated as a distinct series.
    - Accreditation 1973-1974
      - Accreditation of U.M. (includes final report of the ALA Committee on Accreditation) (Box 10)
      - Memos and Correspondence (regarding accreditation) (Box 10)
      - Self-Study Report (materials and reports of the subcommittees)
        - Faculty Subcommittee (Box 10)
        - Governance, Administration, and Financial Support Subcommittee (Box 10)
        - Physical Resources and Facilities Subcommittee, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Program Goals and Objectives Subcommittee (Box 10)
        - Questionnaires Subcommittee (Box 10)
        - Students Subcommittee (Box 10)
      - Steering Committee (Box 10)
    - Accreditation Reports to the ALA Committee on Accreditation
      - 1975-1976 (Box 10)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 10)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 10)
    - Affirmative Action
      - Correspondence and Memos 1968-1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Black Action Movement Dispute 1970 (Box 10)
      - "The Speaker," (dispute over allegedly racist film bought by the school) 1976-1977 (Box 10)
    - Alumni-department evaluations 1967 (Box 10)
      (comments by alumni on the department's strength and weaknesses)
    - Alumni Society
      - Board Meeting 1981 (Box 10)
      - Fiftieth Anniversary Fund 1978-1981 (Box 10)
      - General, (includes minutes and correspondence) 1974-1981 (Box 10)